<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="_c74_vig.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<vignette name="Collab-Hub: Connecting" package="Collab-Hub">

  <metadatalist>
    <metadata name="author">Nick Hwang</metadata>
    <metadata name="tag">Collab-Hub</metadata>
  </metadatalist>

<indexinfo category="Basics" title="Hello">Creating objects and connections</indexinfo>


<h1>Collab-Hub: Connecting</h1>

<p>Collab-Hub is a server-based networking tool for sharing control data and events between creative applicationes - built off Node.Js and libraries we've written it work with Max, PD, Arduino, Web, JS libraries, and more. These modules are part of the Max client.</p>

<p>
Other clients for Collab-Hub can be found at <a href="https://www.collab-hub.io">http://www.collab-hub.io</a>.
</p>

<h2>Getting Started with Collab-Hub with Max</h2>
<p>The following steps will guide you through</p>
<ul>
<li>connecting to and disconnecting from the Collab-Hub server</li>
<li>changing your username</li>
</ul>
<p> Later tutorials will cover more advanced topics such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>sending and receiving data</li>
<li>creating and managing rooms</li>
<li>interfacing with other environments</li>
</ul>


<h3>Open the 'Collab-Hub Modules' patch</h3>
<p>Included in the Collab-Hub Max package, is "Collab-Hub_Modules.maxhelp">'Collab-Hub Modules patch'. Open that patch and open the 'Getting Started' tab to follow along.</p>


<techdetail><p>While following along, the <a href="https://ch-server.herokuapp.com">Collab-Hub Web Interface</a> will help you understand your interaction with Collab-Hub. The Web Interface is acting as another user/client on the server, which can do all the same things the Max modules can do: send and receive data, change username, join and leave rooms, observe to published data, and send/receive chat. </p></techdetail>


<h2>Connecting to and disconnecting from the Collab-Hub server</h2>
<p>The <o>CH-Client</o> is the module which connects you to the server.</p>
<illustration><img src="images/00a_CH-Client.png" />The Collab-Hub Client Module</illustration>
<p>Clicking on <m>'Connect'</m> will initiate the connection with the server. </p>
<p>You should receive feedback when connected...</p>
<ul>
<li>the button on the top-right corner of the module will light up. </li>
<li>the 'Connect' button will change to 'Disconnect'.</li>
<li>a 'serverMessage' should appear in the Max Console, with version number of the server. </li>
<li>a 'Username' button with your current username. </li>
</ul>

<b>You are now connected to the server with your username.</b>
<br />
<br />

<illustration><img src="images/00b_CH-Client_Connected.png" />The Collab-Hub Client Module showing a connection to the Server, current username, and list of connected users.</illustration>

<h2>Using multiple <o>CH-Client</o> modules</h2>
<p><b>You can have multiple <o>CH-Client</o> modules in your Max patch, but only one module should be connected to the server.</b></p>
<p>The modules are aware of each other and will only allow one connection to the server at a time. A pop-up dialog window will warn you if you try to connect to the server while another module is already connected.</p>

<illustration><img src="images/00d_CH-Client_Multiple_Connections.png" />The pop-up dialog warning of multiple connections, offering the option to connect with a different <o>CH-Client</o> module.</illustration>
<techdetail>Because only one module can connect to the server at a time, a single user can check their connection and messages using the <a href="http://ch-server.herokuapp.com">Collab-Hub Demo Interface</a>. You will be able see your username on the user list, </techdetail>


<br />
<h2>Disconnecting from the server</h2>
<p>To disconnect from the server, click on the 'Disconnect' button. </p>

<h2>Change your Username</h2>
<p>You can change your username by clicking on your username -- a dialog window will appear. </p>
<p>After you have input a new username, click on 'OK'.</p>
<p>A new 'serverMessage' will appear in the Max Console: 'Username updated:...'</p>
<illustration><img src="images/00c_CH-Client_Change_Username.png" />Dialog for Username input</illustration>
<br />

<Summary><h2>Summary</h2>
<p>The Collab-Hub Client Module is the module which connects you to the server. It is the only module which can connect to the server. All other modules receive information from the CH-Client module. After the client module connects, you can change your usernmame and send a 'simple chat' message to all users.</p>
</Summary>

	
</vignette>
